<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony against the Quakers False-doctrine, and the image they have set up Being a defence of the book called Antichrist transformed. In answer to a little book, published by Giles Barnadiston. And for better information, the image is hereto annexed verbatim, with the subscribers thereof. Published by Geoffery Bullock.</title>
            <author>Bullock, Jeffery, of Sudbury.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5426A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77781)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2421:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony against the Quakers False-doctrine, and the image they have set up Being a defence of the book called Antichrist transformed. In answer to a little book, published by Giles Barnadiston. And for better information, the image is hereto annexed verbatim, with the subscribers thereof. Published by Geoffery Bullock.</title>
                  <author>Bullock, Jeffery, of Sudbury.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and to be sold by Francis Smith, at the Elephant and Castle in Cornhil, near the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170735:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Againſt the QUAKERS <hi>Falſe-Doctrine,</hi> And the IMAGE they have ſet up. Being a Defence of the Book called <hi>Antichriſt Transformed.</hi> In Anſwer to a little Book, publiſhed By <hi>Giles Barnadiſton.</hi> And for better Information, the IMAGE is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed <hi>Verbatim,</hi> with the Subſcribers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Geoffery Bullock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for the Author, and to be ſold by <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:170735:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170735:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> falſe Doctrine, and the Image they have ſet up.</head>
            <p>A Teſtimony againſt thoſe Quakers, and their falſe Doctrines, who call themſelves Elders and Miniſters; and alſo their new invented Image, and all that joyns with it and owns it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that thoſe Elders who call themſelves Miniſters, look upon themſelves and their Image to be equal in Power and Glory, both with the Father and the Son. This Book is given forth in Anſwer to a little Book, given forth in the name of <hi>Giles Barnadiſton,</hi> which I look upon to be but a pretended Anſwer to my firſt Book.</p>
            <p>Friends, When <hi>Iſrael</hi> had forgotten God their Saviour, then <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, with their Jewels made them a Calf, and they danced about the works of their own Hands. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>But you ſay in the beginning of your Book that <hi>Antichriſt's Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> within, is ſetting it ſelf above the Light within in <hi>J. B.</hi> Now that is impoſſible, that ever that Spirit which fell from God, and ſo loſt its Habitation in God, ſhould ever have Power to exalt himſelf above God again in the Sons of Men. But now this agrees with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine you Preach: for you ſay, that the Seed muſt be raiſed, and God muſt ariſe, and none can keep him down, and that the Seed muſt come up and take its Dominion. So that according to your Doctrine then, both Man, and the Darkneſs too, have Dominion over the Light, who in himſelf is God bleſſed for ever; but the Devil both was and is the Author and Father of this Doctrine of yours. For <hi>Adam</hi> in the day of his firſt Creation was above in <hi>Eden,</hi> and the Garden was in God, then might <hi>Adam</hi> ſee what was in his Temple, or Tabernacle: for there are four diſtinct things, or Beings, to be ſeen in the Temple; that is, the Light, and the Darkneſs, the Tree of Knowledg, and alſo the firſt Man <hi>Adam;</hi> who received a Command from God, that he ſhould live in Obedience to God, and not feed upon the Tree of Knowledg; but in the day that he broke the Command of God, then he fell from God, and loſt his Habitation in God; and ſo the Power of Darkneſs took
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170735:3"/>Dominion over him, wherefore it is the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> that came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of Death.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> that is to be both quickned and raiſed by the Spirit of Life; as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The ſame Spirit that raiſed up Jeſus ſhall quicken you;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>you hath he quickned, who were dead;</hi> So it is not the Seed God, nor Chriſt, that is to be quickned, and raiſed, but the firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> who dyed from that immortal life wherein he was at firſt created.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, that I am making War againſt the Light, page the fourth, and that I am puſhing at it: but this Lye remains upon your own heads; and my firſt Book is a witneſs againſt you, wherein I have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that all Sovereignty, Dominion, and Glory, belongs to the Light that is in every Man; but I do declare, and diſown all ſuch, who look upon themſelves to be equal both in Power and Glory with the Light.</p>
            <p>And Friends, you ſay in your Book, page the fifth, that you are able to judg of Spirit as well as Fleſh. Now this I have ſeen, and known by my own Experience; that in one of our <hi>Quakers</hi> Meetings, that one of thoſe called <hi>Quakers</hi> hath both Preached and Prayed; and that ſome of thoſe called Elders and Miniſters, have publickly diſowned the Teſtimony, as not having Unity with that Spirit that Preached and Prayed. And at another time, the ſame Party hath been exerciſed in Preaching, and Praying, and ſeveral of thoſe called Miniſters have been preſent, and they have both owned the Teſtimony; and alſo had Unity with the Spirit that ſpoke, and have incouraged the Party to go on in the work of the Lord, not fearing the Face of Man, nor regarding their Cenſures, nor Judgments: and is not this confuſion in <hi>Babylon,</hi> you tryers of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who ſo plainly contradict one another in your Cenſures and Judgments?</p>
            <p>And you ſay that I am angry, becauſe that Judgment is gone forth againſt me; and yet in the beginning of your Book, you ſay that I went from you. Now that is very true, that I firſt left you, and I alſo at the preſent time, gave forth a Teſtimony againſt you, what were the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that I left you, the which reaſons and grounds are Printed in my firſt Book.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, in page the ſeventh of your Book, that I have made uſe of my knowledg to ſerve <hi>Lucifers</hi> Intereſt, and that he is become my Teacher and Leader.</p>
            <p>Now Friends, I was a Son of <hi>Adam</hi> by Generation in the Fall, and alſo a Son of God by Creation, and I was alſo a Childe of wrath, being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170735:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>under the Spirit of degeneration; then was the Serpent in many things my Teacher and Leader, but now I think that in my meaſure I am made partaker of the Spirit of Regeneration. But Friends, I ſhall forbear declaring any ſtate that is to be injoyed in the Spirit of God, leaſt the Boaſter ſhould get up, as I fear he is gotten up in thoſe who call themſelves Elders and Miniſters, who ſay they ſit in the Heavenly places in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. But Friends, there is none ſits there with God and Chriſt, but thoſe that are free from Sin as God is.</p>
            <p>Again, you ſay in page the fifth of your Book, As the Father ſent the Son into the World, ſo hath the Son ſent you, that ye may be one as the Father is one, and the Glory which the Father gave him, he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and hath Sanctifyed them through the Truth, that they may be one with the Father and the Son. O you high Boaſters, how is it poſſible, that ever any Man, who is begotten by Generation from <hi>Adam</hi> in the Fall, to be equal with him who never fell, in whom dwelt the fulneſs of the God-head bodily: And he was begotten by the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of the Virgin, and ſo he was the Son of God by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration from God; and ſo it was impoſſible that ever he ſhould Fall: and all his days he was a Man free from Sin. But all you who call your ſelves Elders and Miniſters, have been under the Dominion of the Man of Sin, as well as I; but Chriſt never came under that Spirit nor Power.</p>
            <p>Therefore, remember what the Prophet ſaith, <hi>That the Lord's Sword is drawn againſt the Man that is his Fellow.</hi> So Friends, I fear you are exalted upon the Mountains of Imagination, and the Light ſtands in Judgment over you, and alſo your Book will be a Witneſs againſt you, and the Spirit of God in all thoſe that ſeriouſly read it. Friends, I think it had been more ſuitable for you to have looked back, and to have conſidered ſome of the Patriarks, and holy Men of God, who in their day and Generation did err.</p>
            <p>You might have remembred <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Patriark, who when he had loſt the Spirit of diſcerning, grew blind; and then he was reſolved that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould have the Bleſſing, although it was <hi>Jacob's</hi> right to have it. And you might have remembred <hi>Jacob,</hi> who from a wrong Spirit rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he told his Father he dreamed the Sun, the Moon, and the eleven Stars ſhould bow before him. And you might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam,</hi> who from a Spirit of Pride withſtood <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Hath not the Lord ſpoken unto us as well as unto thee?</hi> And you might have remembred <hi>old Ely,</hi> who from a dark Spirit rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Hannah,</hi> who was a Woman of a ſorrowful Spirit. And you might
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170735:4"/>have remembred <hi>Job's</hi> three Friends, who undertook to Judg Cenſure, and Condemn <hi>Job,</hi> but had not Power to convince him.</p>
            <p>And Friends, you write againſt me in page the fifth and ſixth, becauſe I ſaid, whatever is written to thoſe called Churches, it ought to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in and from the Holy Ghoſt; for if <hi>Paul</hi> did at any time ſpeak by permiſſion and not the Lord, it is but a Mans Commandment; and no Man is bound in Conſcience to follow it: for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am of Chriſt.</hi> Now <hi>Paul,</hi> he Baptized, and he alſo Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but yet he had no Commiſſion to do it: And ſo in time he preach'd it down, as <hi>John</hi> did his Baptiſm; but Chriſt in his day neither Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor Circumciſed any Man: wherefore none are to follow Chriſt, as having <hi>Paul</hi> for their Example; but all are to follow Chriſt, their Light within as their only Rule to walk by. Neither ought any <hi>Quaker</hi> ſo called, Man or Woman, to follow the Light within, as having your Orders and Dictates, as a Rule and Guide for them to walk by. Again, you write againſt me, becauſe I ſaid, whatever is written from a ſight, or ſence, or ſenſible part, and not from the Spirit of Revelation, it is not to be owned by the Churches; and you write thus, and ſay in your Book, that implies contradiction, as much as if the Spirits Revelation ſhould put out Sight, and Senſibility, and ſo I would have blind Elders and ſenſleſs Miniſters.</p>
            <p>But Friends, it is the Devil that hath Power to blind the Soul and Underſtanding of Man, and the ſenſible part; wherefore none are to write from that part in them which the Serpent hath Power to blind, for it is the Soul and Underſtanding of Man that receives the Sight. But all are to write both in and from the Spirit of Revelation, which alone hath Power to give the Creature ſight, and to make people ſenſible of their ſtate and condition. And this is the Holy Ghoſt or Spirit of God, which gives the true Sight and can never blind it; for that is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils work, to bring blindneſs over the Minds of People; wherefore if any ſpeaks, or writes, as pretending to teach others, it ought to be in and from the Holy Ghoſt; for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>It is not you that speak, but the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any Man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracle of God;</hi> and it is the Spirit, ſaith <hi>Paul, that makes Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion with Groans that cannot be utered;</hi> for it is the Inviſible Soul and Underſtanding, that is to be Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt. Now the thing Baptized, that is not to ſpeak in the Church, becauſe it hath been both in Error, Sin, and Tranſgreſſion, but the Inviſible Man, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he is to ſpeak in every Veſſel, who redeems the Creature out of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and not the Soul, nor yet the Senſible part, which hath been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170735:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>in Tranſgreſſion; for the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> they are ſenſible Preachers, who declare againſt the manifeſtation of the Spirit; and deny alſo all Revelations from God, and yet they tell People, that if they be ſenſible of their ſtate and condition, it is an evident token of their Converſion. But I ſay, that all People that come truly to know God, they muſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Being, gathered into that Spirit which makes them truly ſenſible; and this is a Childs ſtate, which hath paſt the Tree of Knowledg, and doth witneſs in meaſure of being poſſeſt of the Tree of Life.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, that I run on in my ſenſleſs Stuff, becauſe that I ſaid, the Soul is the Woman in ever Viſible Man. For you ask me, whether I have not preſumed above what is written in the Scripture?</p>
            <p>Friends, I perceive that you have left the <hi>Quakers</hi> firſt Rule, which they were to walk by as their only Guide, which is the Light or Spirit of Revelation within; for when I was firſt convinced and believed in the Light, then you ſaid, the Light within in every Man was the only Rule, the Grace within, the Myſtery of Life within, or Gods Spirit of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or his Law written in the Heart; that was to be the only Guide for the <hi>Quakers</hi> to walk by. But now I do perceive, that you have ſet up your Image, or Paper of Orders, Dictates, and Forms, that they ſhould join with them as their Rule and Guide.</p>
            <p>Friends, I perceive you are determined, page the ſeventh, to ſet up your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and alſo your <hi>Image</hi> and Superiority amongſt the People called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and likewiſe, to Maintain thoſe Doctrines amongſt them, that he that is not juſtified by the Witneſs of God in Friends, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by it in himſelf; and that thoſe that are unreconciled to the Church, are unreconciled to God, wherefore this I have to ſay, and to all antient Friends: Remember, the firſt Teſtimony that was then found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt the People by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> it was thus, All People mind the Light within you, turn to the Light within, believe in the Light, that doth both convince and make manifeſt Sin; and all owne the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it; for that is the word of Eternal Life, and alſo the Saviour of the Soul, and the Salvation of the ends of the Earth; and that this was Gods Spirit, by whom the World was made; who was in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and before the Beginning, and alſo without Beginning of Days, or end of Life. And this they ſaid was the true Light, that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World; and that this Light was both God, and Chriſt, and the only Saviour of Man, and they exhorted all minds to turn to it, as their God and Saviour.</p>
            <p>Now you ſay in your Book, that thoſe that are unreconciled to the Church, are unreconciled to God.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170735:5"/>
            <p> But now, the Church in God, that is Inviſible as God is Inviſible, although it doth conſiſt of Viſible Bodies, and Inviſible Souls, who are Inviſibly redeemed from the Earth by the Spirit of God, to an enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, who is Inviſible; and theſe are the Members of the Church in God, who are only known to God, and not Man, and ſuch are the Members of the true Church that is in God.</p>
            <p>And in every Nation, <hi>Thoſe that fear God and work Righteouſneſs, are accepted of God;</hi> and thoſe that are accepted of God, ſuch are at U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the Spirit of God in their own particulars, and thoſe are the Members of the Church in God, let them be either <hi>Barbarians, Sythians,</hi> Bond or Free: for the Church of God is Univerſal, as the Spirit of God is Univerſal; ſo that in every Nation, People, Language, or Tongue, thoſe that walk according to the Law written in the Heart, ſuch are at Unity and Peace with God.</p>
            <p>But now, there are many Viſible Separations in the World, which are called Churches, who do not know whether they be in God or no; and theſe are the falſe Churches, who make a Profeſſion of him, and yet know him not. And Gods appearance to them is as their Judg and Condemner.</p>
            <p>Now Friends, Chriſt he is the only Head of that Body, or Church, that is in God; and I am ſure, that thoſe only attend upon the Spirits teaching that is within them; for God is able to teach his Church that is in him, better than you can, although there were a thouſand times more of you then there are. Now, many of you have been <hi>Watch-men</hi> of the <hi>Night,</hi> to inform People of their <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and alſo to direct them to the <hi>Light.</hi> But remember what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, who was but a little paſt the <hi>Watchman</hi> of the <hi>Night,</hi> and <hi>then he ſaw him whom his Soul loved.</hi> Now the Church in God they are paſt all Viſible Counſellors, and all Fathers, yea all Judges; for they are come to God the Judg of all, And to the wonderful Counſellor, the everlaſting Father, and the Prince of Peace.</p>
            <p>Now I owne my ſelf a Member of that Church in God, that gives all Authority, and Superiority, and Subjection, both to God and Chriſt, her Husband. For the Church in God is compared to a Woman, cloathed with the Sun; and the Church is alſo compared to a Mans Wife, that lives in Subjection to her own Husband, and is willing to owne him to be her Head; and ſo doth every true Member that lives in God.</p>
            <p>Now the Church conſiſts of Souls and Bodies, who are truly ſubject to the higher Powers, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. Now your Image and Paper of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170735:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Orders, that may ſerve thoſe <hi>Quakers</hi> who are unſtable, and delight to gad abroad from God, and Chriſt their Husband within; but it can never be owned by the Church in God, by ſuch who are faithful to God, who as a chaſt Virgin, delights to keep with her Husband at home.</p>
            <p>Now Friends, I would deſire to know what People or Congregation of theſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> it was that did impower you, or ſet you at work to make them a Paper of Orders, or a Rule or Guide for them to walk by? or, was it not a thing of your own Invention? and if ſome had not ſeen an evil in your carved <hi>Image,</hi> and ſo put a ſtop to it before it came to its Journeys end, it had not lain hid ſo long as it hath done already; if you could have found out a way to have ſet it up ſooner, for you intended that it ſhould have gone to all the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meetings: but now your work goes on apace, (the words that run round about this <hi>Image</hi> are theſe;) <hi>They that are unreconciled to the Church, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled to God;</hi> and alſo, <hi>thoſe that are not juſtified by the Witneſs of God in Friends, are condemned of it in themſelves:</hi> And about this <hi>Image</hi> here danceth thoſe that call themſelves wiſe Men, and Prophets, Judges, and Counſellors, Fathers, and Sons of God, Elders, and Miniſters, who are at work to ſet up this Idol upon its Feet.</p>
            <p>But if it be true what thoſe ſay, who call themſelves Elders, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Sons of God, and that they are the only true Church in God; and that none are like to be juſtified of God, or reconciled to God in their own particulars; but thoſe who own them to be the only true Church in God, and ſo bow down and Worſhip their <hi>Image,</hi> which they have ſet up, and they are reſolved ſhall ſtand upon its Feet: Then it will be ſad for all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> who do not owne and Worſhip this <hi>Image.</hi> For if it be true, as you ſay, then it will be a thing of neceſſity for all People to enquire after this <hi>Image,</hi> that ſo they may come and worſhip it; becauſe thoſe that have ſet it up, ſay, that God hath given his Power to the Church, and the Power that they ſay they have received from God, it is both to juſtify and alſo to judg of Errors; then this Church muſt needs be as Infallible as God is. So that there is no People ſhall need to fear their being led into Error, if they believe as the Church believes, and own the <hi>Image</hi> which they have ſet up, which is their Paper of Orders, and the reſt of their Inventions; then ſuch by them ſhall be admitted to Preach according to the Faith of the Church; and this is <hi>Pope-like,</hi> who hath ſet up his <hi>Image,</hi> the <hi>Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book,</hi> for the Kings and Princes, and their Subjects, as a Rule for them to walk by.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170735:6"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170735:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170735:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170735:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170735:8"/> Now every breaking forth of the Light, or dawning of the day of God within thoſe in whom this day have dawned; they, in the Light that hath appeared, have ſeen many of the Errors that were in the World, among thoſe called Churches, both as to their Doctrines and Practices; but their Souls not abiding Humble and Low in the Spirit of God, which appeared in their Underſtandings, and gave them a true ſight of things, but having gone out from God in their own particulars, and then thoſe heaps of Teachers they have ſet up an <hi>Image</hi> of their own invention, as you have done, and their Souls have been ſo blinded, and their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings ſo darkned, by the Spirit of Error, that they could never diſcern any evil that there was in their own <hi>Image,</hi> that they have ſet up by their own inventions.</p>
            <p>Let this thing be taken into Conſideration by thoſe that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters and Elders.</p>
            <p>Now your Book ſaith, in page the ſeventh, <hi>That theſe that are unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church, are unreconciled to God;</hi> but the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World to himſelf.</hi> And again, your <hi>Image,</hi> or Paper of Orders, declares, <hi>That he that is not Juſtified by the witneſs of God in Friends, is Condemned of it in himſelf:</hi> But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He that believeth, hath the witneſs in himſelf.</hi> And if Gods wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a Man juſtifies a Man, his Witneſs and Juſtification is greater then yours; ſo that the words of your <hi>Image</hi> are falſe, and contrary to the Scripture, and form of ſound Words.</p>
            <p>Friends, you ſhould do well, if you can, to vindicate both your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and Practices, by ſome evident proof; either from the Spirit of Truth, or the Scriptures of Truth; and if you cannot prove your Doctrine, and the ſetting up of your <hi>Image,</hi> Orders, and <hi>comely Forms,</hi> as you call them, in thoſe which you call your Churches, either from the Scriptures of Truth, or by the Spirit of Truth, and ſo prove them by Revelation from God, and make God to be Author of your falſe Doctrines, and alſo the Father of your <hi>Image,</hi> otherwiſe, they muſt be held forth, and alſo managed by Satan in you transformed into an Angel of Light. But now I do believe that thoſe Doctrines and Practices of yours which I have writ againſt, were never revealed to you from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Spirit of God, but they roſe out of Hell.</p>
            <p>Now in page the eighth of your Book, you write againſt me, becauſe I deny the Reſurrection of the Power, or the ariſing of the Seed or God in Man; the which Doctrines I did deny in my firſt Book, and do ſtill deny them: for it was neither the Seed, nor God, that fell from Heaven into Bondage and Captivity in the Sons and Daughters of Man, but it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170735:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>was the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> that fell both Soul and Body; and we were his Generation, having been in the Fall as well as he. And you alſo ſay <hi>that Chriſt deſcended to bring Man out of the Fall.</hi> Then according to your own confeſſion it is the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> which God created and made, that fell into Tranſgreſſion: ſo then it both was and is the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> that is to be both quickned, and alſo raiſed by the Spirit of Life, that never ſinned, the which is God manifeſting himſelf in theſe earthly Tabernacles by his own Spirit. But now the Holy Ghoſt never deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the Virgins Womb, for the raiſing the Seed or God out of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and Captivity, but the Spirit of God doth deſcend in the Sons and Daughters of Men for the bruiſing the Serpents Head, and for raiſing and bringing of them both Soul and Body to an enjoyment of God again. But yet I do own the Power to be both the Reſurrection and the Life, as he is in himſelf; and he is alſo Mans Reſurrection and Life, as he comes to believe in the Light, and obey it; ſo Man comes to be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and alſo raiſed from under the Power of Death by the Spirit of Life, and ſo brought into an enjoyment of Light and Life again.</p>
            <p>For the Seed did never deſcend in Man for the quickning and raiſing up of the Seed in Man; neither doth the Spirit of God deſcend to raiſe up God in Man, nor yet Chriſt within never deſcended to raiſe up the Spirit of Chriſt in Man. Now you do ſuppoſe the Reſurrection of the Power, becauſe the Light deſcends and appears to Man whilſt he is in the Fall: but yet it abides not with Man whilſt he is in the Fall, but only to convince him of his Sin, and alſo to condemn him for it. But now if Man hears the Spirit, and believes in the Light, and obeys it, then Man is both Quickned and Raiſed, and brought up to God again, by him who is both the Reſurrection and the Life. Wherefore now look back and remember that God called to <hi>Adam</hi> in the cool of the Day, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had eaten of the Fruit of the Tree of Knowledg, and had broke the Command of God; then God curſed the Serpent, and alſo drove <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> out of the Garden, becauſe of his Sin and Tranſgreſſion; And he alſo placed a flaming Sword againſt him: But ſtill God abode in the Garden, in Dominion over all to <hi>Adams</hi> Condemnation.</p>
            <p>But now in page the ninth of your Book, in contradiction to what I have written, you ſay, <hi>If God be above in all the Sons and Daughters of Men, he is taken in his proper place, and the Devil is in his, and I might have ſpared my pains.</hi> But now I did never read, or heard that God was out of his proper place: for God is in his proper place, and his Throne is eſtabliſhed in Juſtice and Judgment over wicked Men, to their Condemnation, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 11. as well as in Love and Mercy over thoſe that hear him, and obey him.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170735:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> But now the Devil and Man both left their Place and Habitation in God, and the Serpent hath had the Dominion over Man and Woman: for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Darkneſs hath covered the Earth, and groſs darkneſs the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Behold, I am preſſed as a Cart is preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Sheaves.</hi> Again, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Let God ariſe, and his Enemies ſhall be ſcattered;</hi> therefore you do conclude, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Seed of God is underneath, and muſt ariſe. And indeed I once heard once Preach, and in his Declaration did exhort all that had believed, <hi>to feel God to ariſe, and none to keep him down:</hi> from which I do conclude thus much, that the Creature is in dominion over his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and alſo hath Power to keep him down. And another ſaid, <hi>All feel God to ariſe, and take the Dominion over all;</hi> which doth conclude that he is not yet in Dominion over all.</p>
            <p>But now conſider a little; Wherefore did God ſwer in his Wrath that <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould not enter into his reſt? And why did God ſtrive with the old World by his Spirit? was it becauſe his Spirit was in Bondage and Captivity in them, and ſo ſtood in need of help and deliverance from them? Or, wherefore did God ſtrive with us by his Spirit in our youthful days? was it becauſe his Spirit or Seed was in Bondage and Captivity in us, and ſo ſtood in need of our help to raiſe him up out of Bondage and Captivity? or, was it not we that were in Bondage and Captivity both Soul and Body, being under the Power of Death and Darkneſs, and ſo ſtood in need both of help and deliverance by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee Light.</hi> So then it is we that have ſlept the ſleep of Death, that are to be awakened, and alſo quickned; and it is not the Seed, nor God, that is to be quickned, nor yet that are to ariſe out of Bondage and Captivity in the Sons and Daughters of Men. Therefore you muſt find out ſome other interpretation for theſe Scriptures: For is it not written, that <hi>the Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpents head?</hi> then muſt not the Seed of the Woman be uppermoſt, and above the Serpents Head in all the Sons and Daughter of Men? for <hi>the Seed of the Serpent,</hi> as it is written, <hi>ſhall but bruiſe his Heel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not alſo written, that God is the higher Power, and every Soul muſt be ſubject to him?</p>
            <p>And in page 10. of your Book, you ſay, <hi>that I do deny the travelling Seed.</hi> Now this I do deny, that neither the Seed, nor God in Man, travels for their own deliverance; becauſe that neither God, nor yet his Spirit were ever in Bondage or Captivity; but Man both Soul and Body
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170735:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath been under the Bondage of Corruption: So it is we that are to be delivered out of Bondage and Captivity; its we that are to make War in the Spirit againſt the Power of darkneſs, and alſo to travel in the Spirit, that ſo by the Spirit of God we may come to be delivered from the Power of Death, and brought into the liberty of the Sons of God: for <hi>they that overcome, as he overcame in the days of the Fleſh, they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit all things.</hi> Now <hi>the Son of Righteouſneſs did ariſe</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> according as it is written, <hi>with healing under his wings,</hi> According to the promiſe of God to his Prophets of old, that ſo he might put an end to all thoſe things by which they did expect healing or remiſſion of Sins.</p>
            <p>Now in page 7 of your Book you write againſt me, becauſe I ſaid <hi>the Books were paid for out of the Poors Collection.</hi> Now as concerning the <hi>Quakers</hi> buying of the Books when I firſt oppoſed the thing, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three years ago, or more, ſince I oppoſed the buying of them; but if the <hi>Quakers</hi> had continued their buying of them ſtill, then you ſhould not have needed to have ordered that they ſhould be paid for out of the Poors Collection? but the thing was true, and I can prove it out of ſome of their own Mouths. And in the ſame page of your Book you ſay, <hi>that I contend againſt the Truth,</hi> and yet you ſay, <hi>that I am crying up the Light:</hi> Is not the Light and the Truth all one? And is not this Confuſion in <hi>Babylon?</hi> Take it into your Conſideration, and let God's Witneſs judg.</p>
            <p>And in Page 9 of your Book, you ſay, <hi>that he that was dead, is alive, and is riſen over Death and Hell.</hi> Now God who both was and is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, was never dead: for he is without beginning of Dayes, or end of Life. But now we have been dead, as to the enjoyment of the Spirit of Life in us: for the Power of Death and Hell hath had Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us, both Soul, and Body, and Underſtanding; but yet the Power of Death was never over, nor yet above the Spirit of God in us, neither was ever God or Chriſt under the Power of Death and Hell in us. Wherefore it is neither God nor Chriſt that is to ariſe in us; but we are to be raiſed by the Arm of his Power revealed from Heaven. And again, you ſay, <hi>his Power is riſen in thouſands.</hi> Now I do believe many have been quickned, and alſo raiſed by his Power from under Deaths Power: For the Lords Spirit or Trumpet hath ſounded, and the dead have heard it; As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170735:10"/>
            <p> And you ſay in <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>Was not that the Light of the World that died, by which Men are condemned?</hi> Now Chriſt ſaid of Himſelf in the Days of his Fleſh, <hi>I am the Light of the World.</hi> And his holy Life was a Witneſs to his Words, as he was a Man, begotten by the Spirit of God; and he alſo ſaid of his Diſciples, <hi>ye are the Light of the World;</hi> but yet they were not the Salvation of the Ends of the Earth. But now God ſaith, <hi>Look unto me all ye Ends of the Earth, and be ſaved; for I am God, and beſides me there is no Saviour,</hi> Iſa. 43. and 45 chap. and Hoſ. 13.4. And <hi>it is God that ſhews to Man his Thoughts,</hi> as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now Chriſt, as he was the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> died, he <hi>being made of a Woman, made under the Law, died to redeem them from the Law that were under the Law.</hi> The which Law, or Diſpenſation, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were never under, nor yet had any Command for the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them. But now Chriſt as he was God by generation from God, he died not; for the Godhead died not, as I have formerly written. And the ſame God that ever was a Saviour and Salvation to the Ends of the Earth, now is, and not another; and his Appearance throughout all Ages among the Gentiles hath been by his Spirit to the Gentiles, the which Spirit, Law, or Light within, both was and is the Gentiles Schoolmaſter, and Rule to walk by.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. you query, <hi>How came the War in Heaven if the Devil could never get into Heaven?</hi> Now as concerning my Saying, <hi>that the Devil could never get up into Heaven;</hi> the thing both was and is true: I or Chriſt in the days of his Fleſh he then dwelt in Heaven, and in the Power of his Father made war againſt every Temptation of the Man of Sin, and ſo in the Power of his Father he kept him out of Heaven; and ſo did <hi>John,</hi> who was born of the Spirit of God. And as concerning the Scripture ſaying, that the Devil is exalted above all in the Temple of God, above all that is called God; Chriſt ſaith to the <hi>Jews, Is it not written in your Law, I ſaid ye are Gods?</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> was to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a God to <hi>Aaron,</hi> as ſaith the Scriptures. But now the Devil he hath been exalted in the Temple of God above all that is called God, or that is called of God, or made by the Power of God in the Temple of God, but yet he is not exalted above God Himſelf. And</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>We are glad for the Truth and our ſakes, that I printed what I did print.</hi> And you ſay, <hi>That the true Doctrine that</hi> Rome <hi>and the Prieſts own, you own it alſo; but the Antichriſtian Doctrine you deny.</hi> Well, Friends, if this Doctrine be true that <hi>Rome</hi> and you own, that is to ſay, Juſtification and Condemnation by him that died without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> then without any further diſpute your Image muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170735:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>down: For your Image ſaith, <hi>That he that is not juſtified by the Witneſs of God in Friends, is condemned.</hi> So this Doctrine can never ſtand; for <hi>Rome</hi> and you ſay both, that Juſtification and Condemnation is by that Chriſt that died. But and if the Old Chriſt keeps his Dominion and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as to the Juſtifying of People, then your new invented Doctrine and Image can never ſtand opon its feet long.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Friends, ſeeing you do acknowledge to own ſome of <hi>Romes,</hi> and alſo of the Prieſts Doctrine; I query of you, Whether you do own theſe following Doctrines, which <hi>Rome</hi> and the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> do own?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether the Kingdom of Heaven be above the viſible Firmament? And alſo Hell to be underneath the viſible Earth which Men walk upon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether Chriſts viſible Body, that once was upon the Earth, be now above in the viſible Heavens, at the right hand of his Father, and there making Interceſſion to God his Father for Sinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether there be three Perſons, as Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which they call the Trinity, above the viſible Heavens?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether you do believe, that the Souls of Men, Women, and Children be immortal, and ſhall abide for ever?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Whether when Men and Women die, and Soul and Body parts, whether the Soul doth aſcend above the viſible Heavens to an Injoyment of Glory? or whether it ſhall deſcend into Hell, a Place of Miſery and Torment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Whether you do believe the Reſurrection of all the viſible Bodies that have died ever ſince our firſt Parents</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve, <hi>yea all that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Noah's <hi>Flood, and all the World that was drowned at the Flood, yea and all the viſible Bodies of Men and Women which have died both by Sea and Land, from a day old to the longeſt age that ever Man lived; and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe viſible Bodies ſhall ariſe and come to Judgment, and receive their Reward in Miſery and Torment, or elſe in Glory and Happineſs, each one according to their deeds done in the Body; yea Children that never knew what Sin was, nor yet what their Souls and Bodies were?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>And whether you do believe that Chriſt ſhall deſcend from above the viſible Heavens, where the Prieſts and Profeſſors, and</hi> Rome <hi>alſo believe he now ſitteth, and from thence he ſhall deſcend with his viſible Body, and ſhall come and judge the World, both Men, Women, and Children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>And whether you do believe that this viſible Earth ſhall be deſtroyed by fire, and that the viſible Heavens ſhall alſo melt with fervent heat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Friends, ſeeing you do not deny ſome of the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor yet of the Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> but only that which is Antichriſtian, and theſe are thoſe Doctrines that both the Prieſts and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170735:11"/>Profeſſors own. Wherefore I would deſire you to give forth a plain Anſwer both to the World, and me alſo, which of theſe fore-mentioned Doctrines are according to the Truth, and which of them are Antichriſtian and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, &amp; ſo write an <hi>Anſwer</hi> in plain words, that every one that can read may come to underſtand; for the Truth is not aſhamed of the Articles of its Faith.</p>
            <p>Now in <hi>pag.</hi> 11 of your Book you ſay, <hi>that I do exclude the Manhood.</hi> Now I do not exclude the Manhood out of his Place; for the viſible Man Chriſt was the Son of God, by generation from God, full of Grace and Truth. But yet there is a Diſtinction to be made betwixt the Godhead, and the viſible Body in which the Godhead dwelt; for Chriſt himſelf made a Diſtinction, and ſaid, <hi>that his Father was greater than he.</hi> And again he ſaid, <hi>My Doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent me.</hi> And he ſaid to the <hi>Jews, Deſtroy this Temple, and in three days I will raiſe it up again.</hi> Now they had no power to deſtroy the Godhead that dwelt in the Temple, that both was and is a thing impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Now you ſay in <hi>pag.</hi> 12 of your Book, <hi>That I contradict my ſelf becauſe that I ſaid that the Man in the Myſtery was the Womans Part, that was his Soul and Body.</hi> Now the Myſtery that dwelt in Chriſt's Body, that was the Godhead; and the Godhead died not, as I writ in my Anſwer to the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> Now as Chriſt was God, or the Seed of God, or the Son of God by generation from God, he never died: for the Holy Ghoſt died not, neither had the Devil power to tempt him as he was God: for <hi>God cannot be tempted,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture. But as he was the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> the Devil had power to preſent Temptations to his Soul, even whilſt his Soul dwelt in the Godhead. But the viſible Manhood, which was the Seed of the Woman as well as the Seed of God, who dwelt in the Godhead, he was impowered by the Godhead to bruiſe the Serpents head in all his appearances and temptations; and ſo the Seed of the Woman did bruiſe the Serpents head, and ſo he never came under the Devil's power, where both we and our firſt Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> have been. So that Chriſt, as he was Man of the ſubſtance of his Mother, he died; but as he was God, and of the ſubſtance of his Father, he died not; for the Godhead died not. But as for our Souls and Bodies, they, like <hi>Eve</hi> their Mother, have been in Tranſgreſſion; but as for Chriſt's Soul and Body, it never conſented to Sin, nor yet joyned to the Spirit of Corruption.</p>
            <p>And again you ſay, <hi>His goings were of old from everlaſting.</hi> Friends, are not the Lords goings by his univerſal Spirit among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles the ſame now as they were in the days of <hi>Abraham?</hi> for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170735:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>then God appeared to <hi>Abimelech,</hi> King of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> by his Spirit in the night; and was not he a Gentile as well as we? and did not God by his Spirit make known Himſelf to <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Elihu?</hi> were not they Gentiles? And had not the <hi>Samaritans</hi> the Spirit of God in the Days of Chriſt's Fleſh, as well as we have it now? And was God not to be worſhipped in his own Spirit then, as Chriſt ſaid to the Woman of <hi>Samaria?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>pag.</hi> 12 of your Book you ſay, <hi>that Chriſt's Blood had a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in it towards the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> So then according to your own words, there was no real Remiſſion of Sin by Chriſt's Blood that was ſhed upon the Ground. Then I would deſire to know what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have by that Blood, if they had not real Remiſſion of Sins by Chriſt's Blood that was ſhed upon the Croſs, without he Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>pag.</hi> 13 of your Book you ſay, <hi>that I do not tell you by whom</hi> Eve <hi>conceived the Man of Sin, who was the Son of Perdition.</hi> But now I will tell you by whom <hi>Eve</hi> conceived, it was by the Serpent, who had a Conception in her Soul when his Temptation entred her; and the ſame Spirit of Darkneſs that brought Death over her, hath brought Death over us, we having been the Children of <hi>Adam and Eve</hi> in the Fall, and having been captivated by the ſame Spirit of Darkneſs as they were. And you alſo write againſt me, becauſe I ſaid, <hi>there are two Chriſts.</hi> Now did not the true Chriſt ſay, that there ſhall be falſe Chriſts, and they are the Sons of Perdition, who are one with the Spirit of Antichriſt? And are there not two Spirits, two Powers, two Gods, two Princes, two Myſteries? And is not the one <hi>Light</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Darkneſs?</hi> The one is called the <hi>true Chriſt,</hi> and the other is the <hi>falſe Chriſt,</hi> which is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> And yet they bear all one Name in Words, although they be different in Works.</p>
            <p>And you alſo ſay, that I do directly oppoſe the Scripture to ſay, <hi>that Chriſt came not of</hi> David, <hi>nor</hi> Iſrael. Now the words in my Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 23, run thus; <hi>Now Chriſt be neither came of</hi> David, <hi>nor yet of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, not as to his outward appearance as he was a viſible Man, but he came of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Iſrael <hi>both according to the Spirit.</hi> And in the 18 Page of my Book it is written thus, <hi>Now Chriſt he was not the Son of</hi> David <hi>by generation from</hi> David, <hi>as he was a viſible Man; for</hi> Mary <hi>ſhe was a Virgin, and knew no viſible Man. But Chriſt he was the Son of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>by generation from God, he being begotten by the Spirit of God in the womb of the Virgin, and this was the fleſh of</hi> David, <hi>and this was</hi> David's <hi>Lord.</hi> Now let all that read and underſtand conſider whether this is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170735:12"/>not a true Declaration according to the Scriptures, concerning the Fleſh of Chriſt, and of his Generation alſo.</p>
            <p>Again you ſay, <hi>That I and my Brethren are Judges of wholeſom Orders, and commendable Forms in the Church.</hi> Now both <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe that are called Prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> they ſay that they are the true Church, and that their Forms are both in Order, and commendable. But now the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the days of their firſt Convincement, they in the Light did ſee an evil in all invented Forms, both in their own as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and in obedience to the Light they denied the Form that was acted by others, and their own alſo. Now that Spirit that ſets up the Form of Prayer, or that acts the Form, and requires People to bow to the Form that is acted, that is the Spirit of Antichriſt. Now the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God being in all, God requires all to bow to the Spirit, and to worſhip him in the Spirit; and not to worſhip the Form that is acted, although it may be performed by the Spirit of God. There is no ſuch Scripture that I know of.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>pag.</hi> 14 of your Book you ſay, <hi>that I have been a ſhame to you.</hi> But if thoſe words be true, that I have been a ſhame to you; then why did <hi>W. D. R. D. G. W. G. B.</hi> and others of the Quakers labour ſo much with me to keep me ſtill among them?</p>
            <p>And you do alſo accuſe me as if I were an <hi>Hypocrite.</hi> Now If I had given up my Faith to your Church, and to have believed as thoſe called Elders and Miniſters believe, then I muſt have been an Hyprocrite. For then I muſt have believed what your <hi>Image,</hi> or Paper of Orders ſaith; that is, that I muſt be reconciled to the Church, and that I muſt alſo be juſtified by the witneſs of God in Friends; the which I cannot believe. Wherefore I have diſowned both you and that Doctrine, and alſo other of your Doctrines likewiſe.</p>
            <p>And you alſo write againſt me, becauſe <hi>I am for marrying with the Nation,</hi> and for my ſaying, <hi>that God hath made all Nations of one blood.</hi> But you ſay in your Book that the Nations have polluted themſelves, and are gone from God's make.</p>
            <p>But I will ask you one Queſtion, and anſwer me; <hi>Hath King</hi> Charles <hi>polluted himſelf by his marrying of a</hi> Portugal <hi>Woman? Or did</hi> Moſes <hi>pollute himſelf by his marrying of an</hi> Ethiopian <hi>Woman? Or did the two Sons of</hi> Naomi <hi>pollute themſelves by marrying of a</hi> Moabitiſh <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? And had not</hi> Moſes <hi>God's univerſal Spirit within him, to be his Rule for him to walk by, when he took the</hi> Ethiopian <hi>Woman to Wife? And was not the Law Spiritual greater than the Law Moral, or the Law Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial? And hath not King</hi> Charles <hi>a meaſure of the ſame Spirit given
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170735:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>him for a Rule for him to malk by, as</hi> Moſes <hi>had before he received the Law outwardly? And is not the Spirit of God in all the Sons and Daughters of Men, given them of God to be their Rule and Guide to walk by? And had not King</hi> Abimelech <hi>the Spirit of God as well as</hi> Abraham, <hi>and did not he obey the voice of God concerning</hi> Sarah, Abrahams <hi>Wife? And was not the Law Moral, and alſo the Law Ceremonial ended? And doth not the Law Spiritual remain in all the Sons and Daughters of Men to this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again you ſay, <hi>That you are Witneſſes to the Matches in the Land of Iſrael</hi> Now was there ever a more wicked Match in the Land of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab</hi> than there was in the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than the Match between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s Wife? And the Prophet in the Spirit of God was a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt it. So that your Witneſs and God's do not agree.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>pag.</hi> 15 of your Book you ſay, <hi>That God is raiſing up Judges and Counſellours as at the beginning, Men fearing God, and hating Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs.</hi> Now if Buyers of Corn to ſell again, and Tranſporters of Corn, and Managers of great Brew-houſes, and Men entring into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mens Trades, and Men being greater Maulſters than ever they were before; if theſe be the Marks of Men fearing God, and hating Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, then ſome of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Miniſters are the Men.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, I <hi>do not underſtand my own Queries,</hi> becauſe I ſaid, <hi>the Book of the Scriptures is part of the fruit of the Tree of Knowledg.</hi> Now I knew that the Book of the Creation was before the Book of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but if you own what I ſay, that the Book of the Scriptures is the Fruit that the Tree of Knowledg bears, then why do you feed ſo much upon them as you do? For let all that read your Book, and alſo the Letter that was given me, which I diſowned, (which Letter is printed in my firſt Book) and they may eaſily perceive that the Line of your Teſtimony is in the Letter and Book of the Scriptures, and not in the Light and Law written in the Heart; from which Law or <hi>Light within,</hi> which was before time was, and from which in time the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures came. And is not this <hi>Light,</hi> Gods univerſal Spirit, the only Rule for we <hi>Gentiles</hi> to walk by? And was not the firſt Teſtimony that was ſounded by the <hi>Quakers</hi> to direct People to the <hi>Light</hi> within? And they told us that was the only Rule. But now your Images Dictates and Orders, and comely Forms, as you call them, they muſt be the Rule for King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Subjects to walk by. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in his Epiſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. ſo ſay I to the People, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not.</hi> And they were <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as we.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170735:13"/>
            <p> And becauſe I ſaid in my Book, <hi>I was an Informer,</hi> therefore you write againſt me, and ſay, <hi>I may take my Place among the Informers.</hi> But now I deſire no greater place among the Sons of Men, than to be an Informer againſt <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his Miniſters. For God Himſelf was an Informer, for he informed <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe of their wickedneſs; and would alſo have deſtroyed them becauſe the People had made a Calf, and worſhipped it, and they alſo danced about it. And there was alſo a Man of God, who in the Word of the Lord was an Informer againſt both the Altar and the Calves that <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had ſet up, both at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> for the People to worſhip at. And was not <hi>Paul</hi> alſo an Informer, when he wrote to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and told them that <hi>Satau was transformed in his Miniſter into an Angel of Light?</hi> And <hi>John</hi> alſo in the Spirit of the Lord was an Informer againſt the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> when they were gone from God, and fallen into Apoſtacy, then he in the Spirit wrote both againſt them and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and told them that they were grown lukewarm, and had alſo left their firſt Love. And hath not God in the Ages and Generations paſt diſcovered the Sins of his own People? witneſs <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and alſo <hi>David,</hi> whoſe Sins are left upon record?</p>
            <p>And further, you ſay in the end of your Book, <hi>You have omitted many groſs Abſurdities, Confuſions, and Follies.</hi> But I think that you ſhould have done well to have made both my Error, groſs Abſurdities and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies manifeſt in your Book, that People might have known them; elſe how can people believe what you ſay to be true?</p>
            <p>And ſo here followeth ſome Queries for you Elders and Miniſters, ſo called by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> to Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether the Light in every <hi>Quaker</hi> be not ſufficient to juſtify them, although you ſay it is the Light in you that condemns them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the Light in any Man, or Men, be able and ſufficient to ſave or juſtify any other Men but themſelves?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether Men cannot be reconciled to God, except they be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church, called <hi>Quakers?</hi> and whether a Man may not be reconciled to your Church, and yet not be reconciled to God?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the Light in one Man, or Men, hath power to open the Underſtanding of another Man, ſeeing that God hath placed a meaſure of his own Spirit in every Man?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether there be not both Darkneſs and Light in every one that is called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> as well in thoſe called Elders and Miniſters, as any others?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether the Light and alſo the Darkneſs hath not been, and alſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170735:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>is in all the Sons and Daughters of Men, ever ſince the firſt Man <hi>Adam's</hi> Tranſgreſſion?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether the Light in every Man be either the Soul or Spirit of a Man, or whether the Light is not a diſtinct Being by himſelf?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether People are not wholly to depend upon the Light, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or Chriſt within for Life and Salvation?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether the ſame Light or Spirit was not in the Gentiles in thoſe days when Chriſt was in the World in that Body which the Father had prepared for him, although the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelt in Chriſt's body?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Now where was that Fleſh and Blood, and what was it that Chriſt told the People in the days of his Fleſh, that they muſt both eat and drink, or elſe they could have no life in them?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether the Viſible Man Chriſt who was Crucified without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whether his Body or Temple, which was like unto ours, Sin only excepted, was diſſolved or changed into a Spirit, and that Spirit now manifeſted in the Gentiles? or where do you believe that Chriſt's Body now is?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Or whether there was any Viſible Church ſo called, or ſeparation among the Gentiles which have not been bewitched, and alſo led into, error by their heaps of Teachers?</p>
            <p n="13">13. And whether thoſe heaps of Teachers by gathering of themſelves together, and by their Conſultations and taking Counſel one of another, have not brought in Errors and Falſe-Doctrines in and among the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of our Churches of the Gentiles, ever ſince the Night of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy even to this very day?</p>
            <p n="14">14. And whether thoſe heaps of Teachers who have had a ſight given them from Gods Spirit to ſee the Errors of other Teachers among the Gentiles that were before them, and yet have not themſelves alſo run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Errors as well as others? But yet they would not believe it, the Devil had ſo blinded their Minds and Underſtandings, and that with a zeal too, even as he did the <hi>Jews</hi> of old.</p>
            <p n="15">15. And hath not all Perſecution riſen from a blind mad Zeal both as to Words and Actions in matters of Conſcience, under a Notion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of both God, Chriſt, and the Scriptures?</p>
            <p n="16">16. Whether Men muſt come to the Scriptures and outward means firſt, before they can know their duty towards God? And whether they muſt not firſt come to the Light and Manifeſtation of the Spirit within them, before they can learn their duty towards God, or what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of them to do?</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170735:14"/> 17. Whether God be changed, or the way of his making known him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be changed? And whether any Man or Men can come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, as to Life and Salvation, but in and by the Spirit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation? Or whether Men did not know God before the Scriptures were?</p>
            <p n="18">18. Whether any of your Writings, although they ſhould be given forth in and from the Spirit of God, are an Inſtrumental Means to bring People to the Knowledg of God as to the Souls Salvation in theſe days, any more than the Scriptures did bring the <hi>Jews</hi> to the knowledg of Chriſt in the days of his Fleſh, or <hi>Paul</hi> in his days? Or by what outward means did you at firſt come to ſee beyond others? or was it not the Light or inward Manifeſtation of the Spirit, as a free gift from God, that gave you to ſee beyond others, and not by any outward Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings?</p>
            <p>But yet one of your Miniſters, ſo called, ſaid, <hi>that Friends Books were Inſtrumental to bring People to the Knowledg of God.</hi> But if that be true what he ſaid then, is the way of God's making known himſelf to the Sons of Men changed? For Men knew God before there was either Scriptures or Writings by any Man; Neither do I read that ever the Scriptures brought any Man to the Knowledg of God. So that your Writings muſt have Authority in them beyond the Scriptures: For Man at firſt never knew God by the Scriptures, but God hath ever made known himſelf to the Sons of Men by his Light or Spirit that was in them, that is by revealing himſelf unto them</p>
            <p>Wherefore I would have all People that read my Book, take notice of theſe following particulars, which are owned by the <hi>Quakers</hi> which I do diſown.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That none can be juſtifyed by the Light or Witneſs of God in thoſe called Miniſters and Elders amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but all muſt be juſtified by the Light in their own particular, or elſe they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is neither the Light, God Chriſt, nor the Seed that is to be quickned and raiſed up in the Sons and Daughters of Men; but it is the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> that is to be both quickned and alſo raiſed up by the Arm of God's Power revealed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is neither the Soul, nor yet the ſenſible part or Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Man, that is either to Pray or Preach in a Meeting; but it is the work of the Holy Ghoſt to ſpeak in every Man. Therefore what do you miniſter from, and what do you miniſter to in the Sons and Daughters of Men? Or what is that which is to attend your Declaration
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170735:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>in thoſe that hear you? Therefore examine your ſelves by the Light, what Spirit it is that ſpeaks in you.</p>
            <p>I have written this to the Elders and Miniſters of the <hi>Quakers:</hi> becauſe there is nothing to be put to print amongſt them without their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as their <hi>Image,</hi> or Paper of Orders, ſaith.</p>
            <p>And alſo becauſe your Book is written in the vindication of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Body of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the <hi>Image</hi> or Paper of Orders may be known to the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in general, I have here inſerted it word for word, with the names of the eleven Elders that ſigned it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>A Teſtimony from the Brethren, who were met together at <hi>London,</hi> in the third month, 1666. to be communicated to the faithful Friends and Elders in the Countries; by them to be <hi>read</hi> in their ſeveral <hi>Meetings,</hi> and kept as a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> among them,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WE your Friends and Brethren, whom God hath called to labour and watch for the Eternal good of your Souls: at the time</hi> aforeſaid, <hi>being through the Lord's good hand, who hath preſerved us at liberty, met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his Name and Fear, were by the</hi> Operation of the Spirit of Truth, <hi>brought into a ſerious Conſideration of this preſent ſtate of the Church of God; which in the day of her return out of the Wilderneſs, hath not only many</hi> open, <hi>but ſome</hi> Covert-<hi>Enemies to Conflict againſt; who are not afraid to speak evil of</hi> Dignities, and deſpiſe Government: without which we are ſenſible our Societies and Fellowſhip cannot be kept holy and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore as God hath put it into our hearts, we do communicate theſe things following unto you; who are turned from darkneſs to light, and profeſs with us in the Glorious Goſpel throughout Nations and Countries: Wherein we have</hi> travelled, <hi>as well for a Teſtimony againſt the</hi> unruly, <hi>as to ſtabliſh and confirm</hi> them, <hi>unto whom it is given to believe the Truth; which is unto us very precious, as we believe it is alſo unto you, who in love have received it, and underſtood the Principles, and felt the Vertue and Operation of it. In which our ſpirits breath, that we all may be preſerved, until we have well finiſhed our Courſe and Teſtimony, to the honour and glory of our Lord God, who is over all bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170735:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. <hi>We having a true ſenſe of the working of the Spirit, which under a Profeſſion of Truth, leads into a Diviſion</hi> from, <hi>and Exaltation</hi> above the Body of Friends, <hi>who never revolted nor degenerated from their Principles, and into</hi> marks of Separation <hi>from the</hi> conſtant Practice of good and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itient Friends, <hi>who are found in the Faith once delivered to</hi> us. <hi>And alſo unto a ſlight eſteem of their Declarations or Preaching, (who have and do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves as the Miniſters of Chriſt) and of the Meetings of the Lords People, whereby, and wherein Friends are, and often have been preciouſly revived and refreſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And under pretence of keeping down</hi> Man and Forms, <hi>doing down the</hi> Miniſtry <hi>and Meetings, or encourage thoſe that do the ſame. We ſay, the Lord giving us to</hi> ſee, <hi>not only the working of that Spirit, and thoſe that are joyned to it, that bring forth theſe</hi> ungrateful <hi>fruits; but alſo the</hi> evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence and Effects of it, <hi>which are of no leſs importance, than</hi> abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tending to deſtroy the Work of God, and lay waſte his Heritage. <hi>We do unanimouſly (being thereto encouraged by the Lord, whoſe preſence is with us) declare and teſtifie, That neither</hi> that <hi>Spirit, nor ſuch as are</hi> joyned <hi>to it, ought to have any</hi> Dominion, Office, or Rule in the Church <hi>of Chriſt Jeſus, whereof the Holy Spirit that was poured forth upon</hi> us, <hi>bath made us Members, and Overſeers. Neither ought they to act, or order the affairs of the ſame: But are rather to be</hi> kept under with the power of God, till they have an Ear open to Inſtruction, and come into Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Witneſs of God; of the encreaſe of whoſe Kingdom and Government there ſhall be no end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>We do declare and teſtifie, That</hi> that <hi>Spirit, and thoſe that are joyned to</hi> it, <hi>who ſtand not in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with the</hi> Miniſtry and Body of Friends; <hi>that are conſtant and ſtedfaſt to the Lord, and to his</hi> unchangeable <hi>Truth, which we have received, and are Witneſſes of, and Ambaſſadors, have not any true Spiritual Right, or Goſpel-Authority to be</hi> Judges in the Church, <hi>and as the Miniſtry of the Goſpel of Chriſt; ſo as to condemn you and their Miniſtry: Neither ought their judgment to be any more regarded by Friends, than the judgment of</hi> other Oppoſers, who are <hi>without. For of right, the Elders and Members of the Church (which keep their habitation in the Truth)</hi> ought <hi>to judg matters and things that differ, and</hi> their <hi>judgment which is</hi> ſo given <hi>therein, ought to ſtand good and</hi> valued <hi>among Friends; though it be kickt againſt and diſapproved by them who have degenerated as aforeſaid. And we do further declare and teſtifie, That it is</hi> abominable Pride, <hi>which goeth before Deſtruction, that ſo puffs up the mind of</hi> any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>that he will not admit of any</hi> judgment <hi>to take place</hi> againſt <hi>him: For he that is not juſtified by the</hi> Witneſs of God in Friends, <hi>is condemned
<pb facs="tcp:170735:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>by it in</hi> himſelf; <hi>though being</hi> hardened, <hi>he may boaſt over it in a</hi> falſe Confidence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If any difference ariſe in the Church, or amongſt them that profeſs themſelves Members thereof; We do declare and teſtifie, That the Church, with the</hi> Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>have power</hi> (without <hi>the</hi> aſſent <hi>of ſuch as</hi> diſſent <hi>from</hi> their <hi>Doctrine and Practices) to hear and determine the ſame. If any pretend to be of us, and in caſe of Controverſie will not admit to be tried by the Church of Chriſt Jeſus, nor ſubmit to the judgment given by the</hi> Spirit of Truth in the Elders and Members <hi>of the ſame, but kick againſt</hi> their judgment, <hi>as</hi> only <hi>the judgment of</hi> Man, <hi>it being mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted according to Truth, and conſiſtent with the Doctrine of</hi> ſuch good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Friends <hi>as have been, and are found in the Faith, agreeable to the</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in his People; <hi>Then we do teſtifie</hi> in the Name of the Lord (<hi>if that judgment ſo given be riſen againſt and denied by the party</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:) <hi>then he or ſhe (and ſuch as ſo far partake of their ſins, as to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and encourage them therein) ought to be</hi> rejected; <hi>And having</hi> err'd <hi>from the Truth, perſiſting therein</hi> preſumptuouſly, <hi>are joyned in</hi> one <hi>with HEATHENS and INFIDELS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>We do declare, That if any go abroad</hi> hereafter, <hi>pretending to that weighty Work and Service, who either in Life or Doctrine grieve</hi> good Friends, <hi>that are ſtedfaſt in the Truth, ſound in the Faith; ſo that they are not</hi> manifeſt <hi>in</hi> their Conſciences, <hi>but diſagree to the</hi> Witneſs of God in them; <hi>Then ought they (whatever have been their Gifts) to leave them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, and forbear going abroad and miniſtring, until they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the</hi> Church, <hi>and have the Approbation of the</hi> Elders <hi>and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame. And if any that have been ſo approved of by the Church, do afterwards degenerate from the Truth, and do that which tendeth to</hi> Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>and countenance Wickedneſs and Faction (as ſome have done) then the Church hath a true Spiritual Right and Authority to call ſuch to Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and if they find ſufficient cauſe for it, by good teſtimony, may judg them unfit for the Work of Gods Miniſtry, whereof they have rendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unworthy; and ſo put a ſtop to their proceedings therein. And if they ſubmit not to the judgment of the</hi> Spirit of Chriſt in his People, <hi>then ought they publickly to be declared againſt; and warning given to the Flock of Chriſt in their ſeveral Meetings, to beware of them, and to have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with them, that they may be aſhamed, and Lambs and Babes in Chriſt preſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>And if any man or woman, which are out of the</hi> Unity <hi>with the</hi> Body of Friends, <hi>print, or ceaſe to be printed, or publiſhed in writing, any thing which is not of ſervice for the Truth; but tends to the</hi> ſcandalizing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching
<pb facs="tcp:170735:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>of faithful Friends, <hi>or to beget or uphold Diviſion and</hi> Faction; <hi>then we do warn and</hi> charge <hi>all Friends that do love Truth, as they deſire it may proſper, and be kept clear, to beware and take heed of having any hand in printing, republiſhing or ſpreading ſuch Books or Writings. And if at any time ſuch Books be ſent to any of you that ſell Books in the Country, after that you, with the advice of</hi> good and ſerious Friends, <hi>have</hi> tried <hi>them, and find them</hi> faulty, <hi>to ſend them back again whence they come. And we further deſire, from time to time,</hi> faithful and ſound Friends <hi>may have the view of ſuch things as are printed upon Truth's account (as formerly it hath uſed to be) before they go to the Preſs; that nothing but what is ſound and ſavory, and that will anſwer the</hi> Witneſs of God even in our Adverſaries, <hi>may be expoſed to</hi> publick <hi>view.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>We do adviſe and counſel, That ſuch as are made</hi> Overſeers <hi>of the Flock of God by the</hi> Holy Spirit, <hi>and do watch for the good of the Church meeting together in their reſpective places, do ſet and keep the affairs of it in</hi> good order; <hi>beware of admitting or encouraging ſuch as are</hi> weak, <hi>and of little</hi> faith, <hi>to take ſuch truſt upon</hi> them: <hi>for by hearing things</hi> diſputed <hi>that are</hi> doubtful, <hi>ſuch may be hurt themſelves, and may hurt the Truth, not being grown into a good underſtanding to</hi> judge <hi>of things. Therefore we exhort, That you who have received a</hi> true ſenſe <hi>of things, be diligent in the Lord's buſineſs, and keep the Meetings as to him, that all may be kept pure and clean, according to that of God which is juſt and equal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We alſo adviſe, That not</hi> any <hi>be admitted to</hi> order Publick buſineſs <hi>of the Church but ſuch as have</hi> felt in a meaſure of the Univerſal Spirit of Truth; <hi>which ſeeks the deſtruction of none, but the general good of all; and eſpecially of thoſe that love it, who are of the Houſhold of Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So, dear Friends and Brethren, believing that your Souls will be refreſhed (in the ſenſe of our ſpirits, and integrity towards God) at the reading of theſe things, as ours were while we ſate together at the opening of them; and that you will be one with us on the behalf of the Lord, and his precious Truth, againſt thoſe who would</hi> limit the Lord to ſpeak without Inſtruments, <hi>or by what Inſtruments</hi> they liſt, <hi>and</hi> reject the Counſel of the Wiſe-men, and the Teſtimony of the Prophets, <hi>which God ſanctified and ſent among you in the day of his Love, when you were gathered; and would not allow him</hi> liberty, <hi>in and by his Servants to</hi> appoint time and place, <hi>wherein to meet together to wait upon and worſhip him, according as he</hi> requireth in Spirit, <hi>and calling it</hi> Formal, <hi>and the Meeting of</hi> Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſay, believing that you will have Fellowſhip with us herein, as we have with you in the Truth, we commit you to God, and the Word of Life, which hath been preached</hi> to you <hi>from the</hi> beginning <hi>(which is neither limited to
<pb facs="tcp:170735:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>place, nor time, nor perſons; but hath power to limit us to each as pleaſeth him) that you with us, and we with you, may be built up in our moſt holy Faith; and be preſerved to partake of the Inheritance which is</hi> heavenly, <hi>amongst all them that are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Richard Farnſworth.</item>
                     <item>Alexander Parker,</item>
                     <item>George Whitehead,</item>
                     <item>Joſiah Coale,</item>
                     <item>John Whitehead.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Loe,</item>
                     <item>Stephen Criſpe,</item>
                     <item>Thomas Green.</item>
                     <item>John Moon.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Briggs,</item>
                     <item>James Parkes.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>This Book is given forth from one who hath born the Name of a <hi>Quaker</hi> this twenty years and more; who was a Son of <hi>Adam</hi> by generation in the Fall, but now an Informer againſt <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his Miniſters, and alſo a Member of the viſible Creation amongſt the Sons of Men, wherein God dwells, called by the Name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jeffery Bullock.</signed>
               <dateline>This Book was given forth by <hi>Jeffery Bullock,</hi> whoſe outward Being is in <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> in <date>the Year 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
